Brothers, The; ead apap081
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Brothers Records
1966-1999
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap081
2.1 cubic ft.
The Brothers was a civil rights group that was active in Albany, New York for several years beginning in 1966.
Historical Note
The Brothers was a civil rights group that was active in Albany, New York for several years beginning in 1966. While picketing a worksite to protest discrimination in hiring practices, Leon Van Dyke was joined by several African-American men from Albany's South End and Arbor Hill neighborhoods. Believing that it was the responsibility of the African-American community to address its own problems, the group took on issues faced by the residents of Arbor Hill, the South End and the North Side: poverty, poor access to health care, slum housing conditions, inadequate public schools and lack of political power. They pressured landlords to clean up their buildings, offered free classes in black history, ran voter registration drives and a breakfast program for poor children. They led rent strikes and protested against discrimination and alleged police brutality. The first action that brought them notoriety was their attempt in November 1966 to expose the alleged vote-buying practice of the Albany Democratic political machine. Considered enemies of the political machine, Mayor Erastus Corning 2nd kept secret police surveillance files on the members. [1] At the height of their prominence the Brothers unsuccessfully fielded African-American candidates for mayor, alderman and county legislator. The Brothers maintained the non-violent philosophy of Dr. Martin Luther King, but indicated that they would react with force if necessary. While not as militant as the Black Panthers, they were viewed with suspicion by many in the African-American community. However, they had the support of many activists in Albany, including lawyers, religious leaders, college students and professors.
Some of the founding members of the group included: Gordon Van Ness, Leon Van Dyke, Clarence Williams, James McBride, John Williams, Sam McDowell, Robert Gene Dobbs, William Gibson, Peter Jones, Herman Washington, Earl Thorpe, James Pryor, and Percell McDowell. [2] There were 15-20 core members of the Brothers. There was no permanent president or chairman. Instead, each week a different Brother took the leadership role so that, according to Gordon Van Ness, ".society can not buy out the Brothers." [3] There were two permanent officers, a treasurer and a secretary. There were seven committees with permanent chairmen: Labor, Welfare, Housing, Political Action, Youth and Drugs, Education and Draft Committees. [4] The Brothers published a newspaper, The Albany Liberator, between 1967 and 1971. It covered news from Albany's Arbor Hill and South End, as well as reprinting articles of interest from all over the country.
The group dissolved in the early 1970s as its members turned their attention to other matters. Some continued their community involvement in less visible ways. After a reunion in April 1990, several former members attempted to revitalize the group. Gordon Van Ness and Clarence Newton opened a community referral center in October 1990 on Clinton Avenue to help advocate for local residents. Shortly after, Van Ness died. Lacking community and financial support, the center closed at the end of 1993. [5]
1. Grondahl, Paul, Albany Times Union, August 22, 1999, p. A32. Gaikowski, Richard, Knickerbocker News, October 20, 1963. Van Ness, Gordon, Original document circa 1964. Ibid 5. LeBrun, Fred, Albany Times Union, December 24, 1993, p.B1
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection was compiled or created by Gordon Van Ness and contains copies of newspaper clippings, original writings, memos and correspondence. The collection includes no formal minutes or correspondence to record the activities of the Brothers. There are, however, papers dated 1970-1972 documenting the efforts of the Albany Medical Center and the Northside Advisory Council to develop and operate a community health facility in the Arbor Hill section of Albany. The majority of the clippings covers the years from 1966 to 1968 and primarily document the activities of the Brothers, the vote-buying controversy, the arrests and subsequent legal proceedings against individual Brothers, the assassination of Dr. Martin Luther King, and articles of interest to the African-American community. Miscellaneous clippings from 1969 to 1999 document issues relevant to the African-American community in Albany, activities of Gordon Van Ness and the deaths of Samuel McDowell and Ronald Brooks. The collection includes a report (unidentified) documenting the disagreement surrounding the arrest of 20 pickets demonstrating outside two polling places in 1966.
There are also original copies, as well as photocopies, of The Albany Liberator published between 1967 and 1971. Peter Pollak, who served as editor of The Albany Liberator, also donated the publication's mailing list and related financials.
Of particular note in the collection are original writings by Gordon Van Ness, most of them undated. Included is a description of the organizational structure of the Brothers, poetry, speeches and highlights of black history and civilization.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. It has no series.
Acquisition Information
The Albany Liberator newspapers in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Barbara Shields in November 1992, Dennis Mosley in 1995, Peter Pollak in 2017, and Dave Michelson in 2019. Other items in this record group were donated by Gordon Van Ness, 1992-1995, Athena V. Lord in 2010, and Peter Pollak in 2017.
Access
Access to the original print copies of the newspapers is not available. Researchers may access preservation copies of The Albany Liberator in Box 2 or digital copies through the archives.albany.edu website.
Northside Community Health Center. Northside Advisory Council.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- New York (State).; African Americans -- Civil rights -- New York (State) -- Albany.; Albany (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Albany, New York; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Ethnic Groups; Van Ness, Gordon, 1940-; Brothers (Albany, N.Y.)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 1, 1967 June 16 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 2, 1967 June 23 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 3, [1967] June 30-July 6 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 5, [1967] July 14-20 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 6, [1967] July 21-27 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 7, [1967] July 28-August 3 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 8, [1967] August 4-10 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, [No. 9], [1967] August 18-24 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 10, [1967] August 25-31 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 11, [1967] September 8-14 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 12, [1967] September 22-28 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 14, [1967] October 13-19 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 15, [1967] October 27-November 2 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 16, [1967] November 3-9 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 18, [1967] December 17 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume I, No. 19, [1967] December 22-[1968] January 11 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 1, [1968] January 25-February 7 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 2-3, 1968 February 29 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 4, [1968] March 28-April 10 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 5, [1968] April 18-May (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 6, [1968] May 9-21 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 7, [1968] June 6-19 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 8, [1968] June 20-July 3 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 9, [1968] July 11-24 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 10, [1968] August 1-14 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 11, [1968] August 22-September 11 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 12, [1968] September 12-25 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume II, No. 13, [1968] October (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Special Issue, Undated (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume III, No. 4, 1970 January 15 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Unnumbered, 1970 April 3 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Unnumbered, 1970 October 23 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume III, No. 2, 1970 November 23-30 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Unnumbered, [1971 January] (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Special Black Arts Issue, 1971 April 15 (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume III, No. 7, 1971 June (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Originals) Volume III, No. 8-9, 1971 July-August (Box 1 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 1, 1967 June 16 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 2, 1967, June 23 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 3, [1967] June 30-July 6 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 4, [1967] July 7-13 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 5, [1967] July 14-20 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 6, [1967] July 21-27 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 7, [1967] July 28-August 3 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, [No. 9], [1967] August 18-24 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 11, [1967] September 8-14 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 13, [1967] September 29-October 5 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 14, [1967] October 13-19 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 17, [1967] November 17-23 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 18, [1967] December 7 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume I, No. 19, [1967] December 22-[1968] January 11 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 2-3, 1968 February 29 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 5, [1968] April 18-May (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 6, [1968] May 9-21 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 8, [1968] June 20-July 3 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 9, [1968] July 11-24 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume II, No. 13, [1968] October 28 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Unnumbered, 1969 October 27-November 3 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume III, No. 4, 1970 January 15 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Unnumbered, 1970 April 3 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Unnumbered, 1970 October 23 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume III, No. 2, 1970 November 23-30 (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Special issue (Sniper Attack), Undated (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Unnumbered, [1971 January] (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Special Black Arts Issue, 1971 April (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume III, No. 7, 1971 June (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator (Photocopies) Volume III, No. 8-9, 1971 July-August (Box 2 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Albany Liberator, Financial Records, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- The Albany Liberator, Mailing List, 1968; Undated (Box 4 (The Brothers Records), Folder 1)
- "A Lesson for All," Gordon Van Ness, Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- "A Letter to a Friend (Inner Cities of America)," Gordon Van Ness, 1990; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- Bibliography on African-American History, 1967; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 4)
- The Brothers' Mission, 1989 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 5)
- Clippings, 1965-1966 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 6)
- Clippings, 1966-1967 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 7)
- Clippings, 1969-1999; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 8)
- Community Newspapers, 1971 (Box 4 (The Brothers Records), Folder 2)
- Community Referral Center, Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 9)
- Flyers and Letters, 1968; 1989 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 10)
- Housing, 1968 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 11)
- Human Relations Seminars for Corrections Officers, 1973; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 12)
- Investigation of Arrest at Polling Place, 1966 November; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 13)
- News Clippings, Albany Publications, 1966-1967; Undated (Box 4 (The Brothers Records), Folder 3)
- Northside Advisory Council (NAC) and Northside Community Health Center (1 of 2), 1970-1972; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 14)
- Northside Advisory Council (NAC) and Northside Community Health Center (2 of 2), 1970-1972; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 15)
- Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Programs (dinners and conferences), 1972; 1975; 1990 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 19)
- Reunion, 1990; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 20)
- Urban League (reports), 1969; Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 21)
- Van Ness, Gordon, Includes undated biographical material and obituary, 1972; 1990 (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 22)
- Writings (original, Gordon Van Ness), Undated (Box 3 (The Brothers Records), Folder 23)